A Guide to the C. Sterling Hutcheson Papers, 1925-1969
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
C. Sterling Hutcheson Papers, 1925-1969
Library of Virginia
32432
16 cubic feet (15 boxes) and 1 microfilm reel
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Betsy Ballou Hutcheson (Mrs. C. Sterling), 8 August 1983.
Biographical/Historical Information
Charles Sterling Hutcheson (1894-1969) was born in Mecklenburg County, near Baskerville, Virginia, and was educated at the College of William and Mary and the University of Virginia. He served as deputy clerk under his father from 1914 to 1918 and was admitted to the Virginia bar in August 1919. He began practicing law in Boydton with his brother, John Y. Hutcheson, and actively continued this partnership until 1944. He married Betsy Wiggins Ballou in 1927. On 3 November 1933 Hutcheson was appointed United States Attorney for the Eastern District of Virginia upon the recommendations of United States senators Harry F. Byrd and Carter Glass. On 19 January 1944 he was nominated by President Roosevelt to be one of two federal judges for the Eastern District of Virginia, and the appointment was confirmed on 8 February. In this position he made major decisions related to school desegregation in Prince Edward County, Virginia. His official headquarters were in Richmond, and he had offices in Norfolk, Newport News, and Alexandria, Virginia. He retired from the bench on 1 September 1959 and continued to hear cases on a selective basis as senior judge. He died in Mecklenburg County, Virginia on 24 October 1969.
Active in many organizations, Hutcheson served them in various positions of responsibility. He was a member of the Board of Visitors of the College of William and Mary from 1928 to 1933 and from 1961 to 1965, serving as rector of the college from 1962 to 1964. In this capacity he worked closely with the newly inaugurated president, Davis Y. Paschall, and was involved in the planning of the new library. He received and honorary degree from the college on 9 June 1968. A member of the Virginia State Library Board from 1961 to 1969, he served as its chairman from June 1964 to September 1969. He was a member of the executive committee of the Virginia Historical Society from 1951 to 1969. He was also a member of the Magna Carta Commission, The Civil War Centennial Commission, and Phi Beta Kappa. He was a Mason and also served for many years on the vestry of St. James' Episcopal Church in Boydton.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1925-1969 (bulk 1933-1969), including files related to Hutcheson's professional career as a jurist, personal files related to his interests and activities with the organizations with which he was affiliated, and papers related to genealogical, historical, and some business interest. Hutcheson maintained a large correspondence with a variety of individuals. A prolific writer with broad, public interests, he appears to have acknowledged most incoming letters, even congratulatory letters for his achievements throughout the years. Correspondents of particular interest include: Randolph W. Church, General Edwin Cox, Virginius Dabney, William B. Hill, George Humrickhouse, W. Moscoe Huntley, Davis Y. Pascall, Governor William Tuck, William J. Van Schreeven. Researchers are advised to consult relevant files in all series for a complete search of an individual's correspondence with Hutcheson.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Folder titles and series have been maintained whenever possible, and the large amount of loose papers, pre-1960, was interfiled in the chronological series of general correspondence because the date range of this series is earlier than the alphabetical series.
Approximately 1.5 cubic feet of newspaper clippings are microfilmed and filed as Miscellaneous Reel 1043.
Organization
This collection is organized into the following series: I. General Correspondence (chronological and alphabetical); II. Family Correspondence; III. Subject Files (Professional and Personal); IV. Writings; V. Printed Material.
Contents List
- General Correspondence 1934-1969
  - Chronological 1934-1969
    Folders marked "CSH" contain correspondence that was fixed in a folder with a metal fastener by Judge Hutcheson. This correspondence remains in that order. Folders marked "loose" contain the loose correspondence filed chronologically
    - 1934-1943 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1944 January-February (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1944 March-December (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1944-1947 (CSH) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1948-1949 (CSH) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1945-1949 (loose) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1950-1951 (CSH) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1952-1953 (CSH) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1950-1953 (loose) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1954-1955 (CSH) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1956-1957 (CSH) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1954-1957 (loose) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1958-July 1959 (CSH) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1958 (loose) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1959 January-September (loose) (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1959 October-December (loose) (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1960 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1961-1969 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1968-1969 secretarial notebooks (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Alphabetical 1942-1969
    Except for the individual files, these folders remain as they were received with no added correspondence
    - A, 1960-1968 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 20)
    - B, 1960-1969, n.d. (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 21)
    - C, 1960-1969, n.d. (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 22)
    - D, 1960-1969 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Captain Miles DuVal, 1963-1964 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 24)
    - E, 1959, 1961-1969 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 25)
    - F, 1960-1969 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Mabel Goode Frantz, 1941-1969, n.d. (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 27)
    - G, 1959-1969, n.d. (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Colonel Lloyd R. Garrison, 1961-1966, 1969 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 29)
    - H, 1960-1969, n.d. (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Eppa Hunton IV, 1960-1968 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Joseph C. Hutcheson (brother), 1957-1967 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Honorable Joseph C. Hutcheson, Jr., 1942-1968, n.d. (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 33)
    - I, 1965-1968 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 34)
    - J, 1960-1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 35)
    - K, 1960-1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 36)
    - L, 1960-1969, n.d. (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Mc, 1960-1969, n.d. (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Rose Goode McCullough (1), 1949, 1954-1958 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Rose Goode McCullough (2), 1958-1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 40)
    - M, 1956, 1960-1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Dr. (Robert D.) Meade, 1954-1969, n.d. (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 42)
    - N, 1961-1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 43)
    - O, 1961-1968 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 44)
    - P-Q, 1963-1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 45)
    - R, 1960-1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 46)
    - James Scott Rawlings, 1961-1963 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 47)
    - F. D. G. Ribble, 1954-1963 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 48)
    - S, 1960-1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 49)
    - T, 1956, 1960-1969, n.d. (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 50)
    - U, 1962-1967 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 51)
    - V, 1960-1967 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 52)
    - W, 1960-1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 53)
    - XYZ, 1961-1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 54)
- Family Correspondence 1928-1969
  - Conway G. Hutcheson, 1944-1949 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-1)
  - Dianitia Hutcheson, 1955-1969, n.d. (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-2)
  - Edward Hutcheson [Houston, Texas], 1962-1968 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-3)
  - H. F. Hutcheson, 1928-1931 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-4)
  - H. F. Hutcheson, Jr., 1950-1963 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-5)
  - Helen Young Hutcheson, 1956-1969 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-6)
  - Dr. J. Sterling Hutcheson, 1957-1969 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-7)
  - James L. Hutcheson, 1947-1960 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-8)
  - Jim Reed Hutcheson, 1956-1962, n.d. (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-9)
  - Jim Reed Hutcheson, 1963-1969 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-10)
  - Joseph C. Hutcheson, 1942-1954 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-11)
  - Nat Hutcheson, 1949, 1958, n.d. (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-12)
  - Sterling H. Hutcheson [San Diego, California], 1961-1969 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-13)
  - William C. Hutcheson, 1942-1958, n.d. (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-14)
  - William C. Hutcheson, 1959-1964 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-15)
  - William C. Hutcheson, 1965-1969 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-16)
  - Toyne Family, 1948-1962, n.d. (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-17)
  - Other Family Members, 1934-1968 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-18)
  - Estate of Conway G. Hutcheson, 1952-1955 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-19)
  - Estate of Herbert F. Hutcheson, 1952-1955 (Box-folder Box 3A, Folder 54-20)
- Subject Files
  - Professional
    - Administrative Office, 1960-1962 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Administrative Office, 1963-1967 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Administrative Office, 1967-1969 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Alexandria Cases, 1962 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Alexandria Cases, 1963 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 59)
    - [Appointment as] United States Attorney, August 1933 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Appointment as United States District Judge for Eastern District of Virginia, 1944, 1947 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Alfred Avins, 1962-1963 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Judge Barksdale [A. D. "Dick"], 1961-1969 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Frances Beidler II, etc., v. Veno, etc., 1962 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Brown v. United States - U. S. Court of Appeals (4th) 8205, 1960 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Judge Albert V. Bryan, 1959-1967, 1969 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Judge Butzner [John D., Jr.], 1962-1967 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Harry F. Byrd, 1957, 1959-1968 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Ruth B. Cain, etc., v. John H. Beecher, etc., 1962 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Central States Electric, 1962, 1965-1966, 1968-1969 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Circuit Court of Appeals, letters of endorsement for appointment to, 1956 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Honorable Ted Dalton, 1964-1965, 1969 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 72)
    - C/A 2740 S. C. - Bertha Preston Darter and O. L. Darter v. Greenville Community Hotel Corp., 1959-1961 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 73)
    - C/A 2775 S. C. - Edna Mae Eubanks vs. Piedmont Natural Gas Co., Inc., a Corp., and Louisiana-Mississippi Pipe Line Construction Co., a Corp., 1960-1961 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Expenses, 1960-1967, 1969 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Charles Garian, 1960-1961, 1963, 1965, 1969 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Evelyn S. Gilbert, 1960-1965 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Governor Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1966-1967, 1969 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Willis E. Grange v. State of South Carolina, 1960-1961 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Great American Ins. Co. v. Harleysville Mutual, 1960 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Albertis S. Harrison, Jr., 1961, 1964-1965, 1967, 1969 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Judge Clement F. Haynsworth, Jr., 1964-1965, 1969 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Heyl and Patterson v. McDowell, etc., 1960 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Judge Hoffman [Walter E.], 1960-1965, 1967, 1969 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Harry H. Holt, Jr., U. S. Attorney, 1947 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Walkley E. Johnson, Misc., 1960-1965, 1968, 1969 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 86)
    - Judicial Conference, 1966 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Judicial Conference, 1967 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 88)
    - Judicial Conference, 1968 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Judicial Conference, 1969 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Judicial Robes, 1948, 1954, 1956-1957 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Judicial Vacations, 1957 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Lois R. Kaesshafer, 1961 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Judge Oren R. Lewis, 1960-1963, 1965, 1967, 1969 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 94)
    - Markham v. City of Newport News, 1960 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Charles N. Matthews, U. S. v., 1958-1960 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Charles N. Matthews, 1958, 1960-1968 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Honorable Robert R. Merhige, Jr., 1967-1969 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 98)
    - David J. Mustin, etc., v. Al-Con, etc., 1961 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 99)
    - NAACP, 1959-1961, 1964-1965 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 100)
    - C/A 2355 S. C. - Albert F. Newman vs. G. and G. Auto Wrecking Co., A Corp., 1961 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Newport News, cases heard during weeks of February 1 and February 15, 1960 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 102)
    - Newport News, 1961, 1962, 1964 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Eastern District of North Carolina, 1960-1965 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Office Space, 1960, 1963-1969 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 105)
    - Judge Paul [John], 1958-1961, 1963 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 106)
    - [Pension], H. R. 6974 providing for pensions for widows and dependent children of Federal judges, 1956-1957 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 107)
    - [Personnel], Marie B. Grubbs, deputy clerk, re. dismissal, 1947 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 108)
    - [Personnel], C. K. Moran, clerk, 1947 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Photographs (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Prisoners' Correspondence, 1961-1969 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 111)
    - Elva W. Puryear, 1960-1963 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 112)
    - [Retirement]: 1959 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 113)
    - [Retirement]: Application of Civil Service Retirment Act to Judges, 1949-1952 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 114)
    - [Retirement]: Refund of retirement deductions as United States Attorney, 1944-1945 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 115)
    - Retirement of Judges, 1955-1956 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 116)
    - Richmond Trial Work, 1960-1964 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 117)
    - Richmond [Trial Work], June 1964 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 118)
    - Richmond Trial Work, October 1964 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 119)
    - Richmond Trial Work, December 1964 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 120)
    - Richmond [Trial Work] District Court, March 1965 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 121)
    - Richmond Trial Work, May 1965 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 122)
    - Richmond [Trial Work], November-December 1965 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 123)
    - Richmond Trial Work, 1966 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 124)
    - Richmond Trial Work, 1967 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 125)
    - Richmond Trial Work, October 1967 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 126)
    - Richmond Trial Work, 1968 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 127)
    - Richmond Trial Work, 1969 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 128)
    - A. Willis Robertson, 1963-1964 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 129)
    - Salaries of Judges, 1953, 1955 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 130)
    - Secretary (Dawson Hale), 1960 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 131)
    - Segregation: Miscellaneous Literature [and correspondence], 1955-1958 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 132)
    - [Segregation]: Prince Edward [County], 1957-1958 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 133)
    - Segregation Cases, School, 1957-1958 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 134)
    - Segregation Question, 1957-1958 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 135)
    - Jack Shelton v. State of South Carolina, vs. Court of Appeals (4th), 1960 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 136)
    - Shepard's Citations, 1960 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 137)
    - Robert C. Smith, Norfolk, Virginia, 1960, 1962-1963 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 138)
    - Judge Simon E. Sobeloff, 1960-1964, 1969 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 139)
    - Judge Morris A. Sopher, 1960-1961 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 140)
    - Sound Scriber, 1961 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 141)
    - South Carolina, 1961 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 142)
    - Supplies, 1960-1961, 1963 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 143)
    - Typewriter Repair, 1961, 1963-1967 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 144)
    - U. S. Court of Appeals, 1964 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 145)
    - U. S. Court of Appeals, April 1964 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 146)
    - U. S. Court of Appeals, January 1965 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 147)
    - U. S. Court of Appeals, 2 March 1965 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 148)
    - U. S. Court of Appeals, May-June 1965 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 149)
    - U. S. Court of Appeals, February 1966 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 150)
    - U. S. Court of Appeals, 1967 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 151)
    - U. S. Court of Appeals, 1968-1969 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 152)
    - U. S. of America v. Chesapeake and Ohio Railway No. 1477, 1960 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 153)
    - Elmer Wilson Walker B-322-NE, 1962 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 154)
    - Western District - U. S. Courts, 1969 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 155)
    - Wildlife, 1960-1961 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 156)
    - Judge Ashton H. Williams, 1961 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 157)
    - R. M. F. Williams, Jr., 1960-1963 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 158)
    - Judge Cecil C. Wyche, 1960-1961, 1965 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 159)
    - Opinions, 1945-1955 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 160)
    - Opinions, 1956-1959 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 161)
    - Opinions - Agency-liability of morte (?) for misconduct of servant (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 162)
    - Opinions - Arbitration-jursidiction-summary judgment (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 163)
    - Opinions - Bankruptcy (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 164)
    - Opinions - Bribery (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 165)
    - Opinions - Citizenship (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 166)
    - Opinions - Collision-ship-Admiralty (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 167)
    - Opinions - Condemnation/land (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 168)
    - Opinions - Conspiracy (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 169)
    - Opinions - Contract, break of (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 170)
    - Opinions - Death cases (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 171)
    - Opinions - Death by wrongful act (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 172)
    - Opinions - Embezzlement (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 173)
    - Opinions - Fair Labor Standards Act (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 174)
    - Opinions - False Arrest (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 175)
    - Opinions - Fed. Emp. Liability Act (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 176)
    - Opinions - Fed. Tort Claims Act (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 177)
    - Opinions - Forfeiture (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 178)
    - Opinions - Fraud (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 179)
    - Opinions - Habeas Corpus (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 180)
    - Opinions - Infringement-copyright (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 181)
    - Opinions - Innkeepers-liability for loss of guests' possessions (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 182)
    - Opinions - Insurance (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 183)
    - Opinions - Interstate Commerce (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 184)
    - Opinions - Maritime Tort (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 185)
    - Opinions - Patent Infringement (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 186)
    - Opinions - Personal Injury (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 187)
    - Opinions - Price Control (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 188)
    - Opinions - Real Estate (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 189)
    - Opinions - Receivership (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 190)
    - Opinions - Reorganization (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 191)
    - Opinions - Salvage-Admiralty (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 192)
    - Opinions - Seamen-personal injuries (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 193)
    - Opinions - Seamens' wages, etc. - Adm. (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 194)
    - Opinions - Segregation (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 195)
    - Opinions - Ship Collision-adm. (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 196)
    - Opinions - Slander (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 197)
    - Opinions - Tax Evasion (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 198)
    - Opinions - Tax Refund (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 199)
    - Opinions - Value-method of determining value of vessel taken by gov't (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 200)
    - Opinions - Veterans' Preference Act (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 201)
    - Opinions - Wage-hour (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 202)
    - Opinions - Wage claim-authority (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 203)
    - Opinions - Loose Opinions (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 204)
    - Opinions - Printed Opinions (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 205)
    - Speeches, 1941-1960 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 206)
      - At reunion of descendants of Alexander Boyd, the Elder - "Xanderwood," Boydton, 16 August 1941
      - Tribute to Col. J. Thomas Goode at portrait presentation - Mecklenburg County Courthouse, Boydton, 26 October 1946
      - At the 200th anniversary of the birth of Chief Justice John Marshall - Marshall House, Richmond, 24 September 1955
      - For the Richmond Bar Association - John Marshall Hotel, Richmond, 28 September 1955
      - Conference for Lawyers, "Ethical Dilemmas Faced in My Daily Job" - Roslyn, 4 February 1956
      - Occoneechee Park, 4 May 1957
      - Re. Constitutional Government, 1959
      - Re. Extra Session of General Assembly, 1959
      - At U. Va. Law School?, 1959
      - At Joint A.P.V.A - D.A.R. meeting, March 1960
      - Under Auspices of the Prestwould Chapter D.A.R. - Park View High School, 2 March 1960
      - Association of Legal Secretaries, "Origin of the Courts" - Richmond, 19 March 1960
      - Women of St. James Church, Boydton, 30 March 1960
      - Mecklenburg County Bar Association, Chase City, 2 December 1960
      - At Roanoke County Bar Association, Chase City, 2 December 1960
      - At Roanoke River Branch, A.P.V.A., 10 December 1960
    - Speeches, 1961-1966 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 207)
      - "The Expansion of the Federal Government's Control Over the Activities of the Individual - Some Comments Concerning Judicial Action in this Area" - University of Virginia Law School, William H. White Memorial Lecture, March 1961
      - Baskerville Woman's Club, June 1961
      - "A Brief History of Boydton" - 150th Anniversary of Charter, Boydton Court Room, 18 August 1962
      - "Women Spies for the Confederacy" - Armistead-Good Chapter U.D.C., Boydton 12 November 1962
      - "Some Comments Concerning the Past, Present and Future of Constitutional Government in America" - Granville-Warren Committee of the National Society Colonial Dames of America in state of North Carolina, Oxford, N.C., 20 May 1964
      - Danville Branch, AAUW, 28 February 1966
    - Speeches - By Others (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 208)
    - Speeches - Correspondence relating to, 1955, 1959-1960, 1965-1966 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 209)
    - College of William and Mary, 1962 January-June (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 210)
    - College of William and Mary, 1962 April 28 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 211)
    - College of William and Mary, 1962 July-August (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 212)
    - College of William and Mary, 1962 September-December (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 213)
    - College of William and Mary - Richard Bland College, 1962, 1963 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 214)
    - College of William and Mary, 1963 January-March (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 215)
    - College of William and Mary, 1963 April-July (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 216)
    - College of William and Mary - Commencement 1963 June (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 217)
    - College of William and Mary, 1963 August-September (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 218)
    - College of William and Mary, 1963 October-December (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 219)
    - College of William and Mary, 1964 January-February (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 220)
    - College of William and Mary, 1964 March-April (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 221)
    - College of William and Mary, 1964 May-December (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 222)
    - College of William and Mary, 1965 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 223)